<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Cristina Hartmann]]></title>
  <link href="http://cmmhartmann.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://cmmhartmann.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-01T20:02:47-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://cmmhartmann.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Cristina Hartmann]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Defence of Junk Fiction]]></title>
    <link href="http://cmmhartmann.com/blog/2013/09/26/a-defence-of-junk-fiction/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-26T19:00:47-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://cmmhartmann.com/blog/2013/09/26/a-defence-of-junk-fiction</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hi, my name is Cristina. I am a junk fiction lover. Nice to meet you.</p>

<p>My reading taste vacillates somewhere between a slightly raised middlebrow to a droopy lowbrow, depending on my mood. (Right now, it&rsquo;s in the lower half.) Whatever my mood may be, I am always a fan of junk fiction.</p>

<p>Junk fiction isn&rsquo;t a real genre, but it&rsquo;s what I call books that has a vocabulary that hovers above a fifth-grade level and will never win any literary awards. They are oftentimes formulaic and employ hackneyed plot devices. In other words, these are the books that you&rsquo;re at least a bit embarrassed to admit reading among your well-educated and well-read peers.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m here to defend these books. They may be a little trashy, but they are worthwhile.</p>

<h3>Junk Fiction as a Gateway Drug</h3>

<p>Junk fiction, true to its name, appeals to our less refined tastes and is easy to consume. When the most challenging word in the book is motherfucker, you don&rsquo;t need to keep your dictionary nearby. With these formulaic plot lines, you can breeze through a book in a day or two.</p>

<p>Maybe, in this case, a low nutritional content is a good thing.</p>

<p>Let me tell you how I got into reading grown-up books. When I made my first tentative steps from the YA stacks in the library to the big, scary adult section, I didn&rsquo;t know where to start. As a 11-year-old, I wasn&rsquo;t sure how to choose books so I simply looked at the top 100 books and chose the one with the coolest cover. Well, I began with A Portrait of a Lady, and gave up after 20 pages. I slunk back to the YA section, convinced that I wasn&rsquo;t grown-up enough and re-read A Face on the Milk Carton for the umpteenth time.</p>

<p>A year later, I gathered up my courage and ventured back into the grown-up books section. This time I picked up a Clive Clusser book. (Cool cover, bro.) I loved it and read some more. They were easy to read, action-packed, and didn&rsquo;t constantly confuse me.</p>

<p>From Clive Clusser, I graduated to Dean Koontz, Stephen King, John Grisham, Robert Ludlum, and I think Dan Brown made an appearance. With these writers, my vocabulary expanded, my ability to follow more complex plots improved, and my confidence in my reading abilities skyrocketed.</p>

<p>So, I moved onto the harder stuff: Steinbeck, Garcia Marquez, Nabokov, the Bronte Sisters, Austen, among others. I doubt I would have been able to bear 100 Years of Solitude with its dozens of Aurelianos and irregular chronology without my background in junk fiction.</p>

<p>Of course, this is all anecdotal evidence and wouldn&rsquo;t pass snuff even at the most drug-addled review panel. Now we&rsquo;ll talk about harder things like facts and statistics.</p>

<p>In the age of junky YA fiction like Twilight, The Hunger Games, not to mention the whole paranormal thang, the future of reading may seem dim. Yet, teens and young adults (between the ages of 16 and 29) read far more than their older peers.[1][2] I suspect that they&rsquo;re not all reading James Joyce, but they&rsquo;re reading stuff like Fifty Shades of Grey and paranormal adventures.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t think this is a bad thing at all. I think it&rsquo;s great. Books like Twilight and The Hunger Games, are a great introduction to the wide world of literature. Once teens read these books, they will see that books can be fun and cool to read. Some of them will even take bold steps further into the  literary world into more difficult reads like Austen and, god forbid it, Cormac McCarthy.</p>

<p>As they say, you catch more flies with honey than with vinegar. That being said, by slowly increasing the amount of vinegar in honey, maybe you can teach the fly to like vinegar.</p>

<p>Of course, not everyone will make the transition from junk fiction to the harder stuff. That&rsquo;s okay. Not everyone is cut out to read Infinite Jest on the bus ride to work. You know, a lot of pot users never graduate to LSD, cocaine, or the harder stuff&hellip;they&rsquo;re just there for the soft buzz. Quite frankly, these folks would never have come close to Tolstoy anyway, no matter how much honey you pour on Anna Karenina.</p>

<h3>The Value of Simple Entertainment</h3>

<p>Junk fiction serves a even loftier purpose than serving as a gateway drug: it entertains.</p>

<p>In certain circles, people look down on books, movies, and activities that are entertaining for the sake of entertainment. I think they feel like a human mind should constantly run on full capacity. If you slip and read a sentence from a Dan Brown book, your life will be ruined.</p>

<p>You know, sometimes it&rsquo;s fun just to have&hellip;fun.</p>

<p>I can cite research saying that fun is important to things like success, brain functioning, sex drive&hellip;whatever, but that&rsquo;d be capitulating to the incessant push to improve ourselves.[3] All I know is that I hate the feeling of having to be running on every cylinder at all times. Sometimes I just want to relax, bro.</p>

<p>The beautiful thing about today&rsquo;s literary world is that, no matter your taste, you can find a book that tickles your fancy. Be it lowbrow swords-and-dagger romance, or teenage fantasies about hot vampires, you have an opportunity to escape our stressful realities.</p>

<p>I just wanna have fun sometimes, y&#8217;know? Being deep is hard and stuff.</p>

<hr />

<p>[1]: <a href="http://www.takepart.com/article/2012/10/24/young-americans-reading-habits-may-surprise-you">Teens in America: Why Their Reading Habits May Surprise You</a><br/>
[2]: <a href="http://www.scholastic.com/content/collateral_resources/pdf/i/Reading_for_pleasure.pdf">Page on Scholastic</a><br/>
[3]: <a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/danschawbel/2012/07/25/why-you-need-to-have-fun-to-be-successful/">Why You Need to Have Fun to Be Successful</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writers v. Storytellers: An Epic Battle? Nah.]]></title>
    <link href="http://cmmhartmann.com/blog/2013/06/18/writers-v-storytellers-an-epic-battle-nah/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-18T19:24:28-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://cmmhartmann.com/blog/2013/06/18/writers-v-storytellers-an-epic-battle-nah</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been rolling this question around in my mind for a while: why do certain authors captivate the imagination without seeming to have a droplet of writing skills?</p>

<p>It causes much grief when we see books such as Twilight, Da Vinci Code gain bestseller success while finely crafted books lay unread and collecting dust on the bookshelves. These two examples aren&rsquo;t what most would call &ldquo;good&rdquo; books in the literary sense. Their language hovers slightly above a fourth-grade level. Their characters defy the concept of &ldquo;character development.&rdquo; The plots veer towards the silly and improbable.</p>

<p>Yet, people love them.</p>

<p>There are other books that have prose that tickles the five senses, characters the have deep, complex layers and plots that excite. These are what critics would call &ldquo;good&rdquo; books. These books win literary prizes. The aforementioned books don&rsquo;t.</p>

<p>To me, these books seem so different that it&rsquo;s almost unfair to compare them at all. I feel like I&rsquo;m comparing apples with oranges when I put a Danielle Steele novel next to The Great Gatsby.</p>

<p>So, maybe we shouldn&rsquo;t compare them at all. Perhaps these two types of books come from very different creatures: storytellers and writers.</p>

<h3>Storytellers are the Makers of Mass-Produced Writing</h3>

<p>Now, I don&rsquo;t want to disparage either mass-producers or these storytellers. Authors like Meyer and Dan Brown don&rsquo;t seek to elevate their craft, but their stores sell. Mass producers, like these authors, just want to sell stuff and fulfill a function. Meyer and Brown are what I&rsquo;d categorize as pure storytellers.</p>

<p>Pure storytellers tell a story that hooks a large audience, compelling them to read pages upon pages of twists and turns. Their writing never reaches the &ldquo;exquisite&rdquo; level, or sometimes even the &ldquo;decent&rdquo; level. Their prose can be hackneyed, cliche-ridden and simplistic. Their characters feel flat and unrealistic.</p>

<p>Yet, their stories zoom to the top of the New York Times bestselling list.</p>

<p>Like mass-produced furniture, storytellers emphasize functionality over artistry. They look for things that will please a lot of people, such as exciting plots, improbable events and relatable characters. Mass-producers of furniture make couches and tables for people to use, not to serve as pieces of useful (?) art. Storytellers don&rsquo;t seek to revolutionize the literary world. They just want to entertain people. People want to be entertained in a mindless way, just like people want a simple piece of furniture to sit on.</p>

<p>Just like furniture gains, there are the good ones (IKEA) and there are bad ones (no-name shops). The writers of the IKEA variety like to inject some spirit, some modernity, and some sass into their writing. Think: George R. R. Martin, Alexandre Dumas, and arguably Stephen King. The writers of the no-name brand variety may look from far away, but upon closer inspection, have shoddy construction. Think: Dan Brown, Stephenie Meyer, along others. Beware of the latter, you may fall down when you sit on those things.</p>

<p>Writers are Fine Craftspeople. One must have the right background to appreciate their art.</p>

<p>Writers want to contribute something to the craft. They want to create a work of art. They don&rsquo;t care about pleasing the masses. They oftentimes write beautiful prose that makes people gasp. They explore the underbelly of human nature.</p>

<p>These are the books that, as you read them, you think, &ldquo;This is some fine writing.&rdquo; You&rsquo;ll recommend the book to all of your friends. All but one or two will never pick up the book, let alone enjoy it. It&rsquo;s a piece of art, but not appreciated by everyone. It&rsquo;s just not entertaining enough. The story may peel away our poor veneers and expose baser truths, but it&rsquo;s just doesn&rsquo;t leave you breathless.</p>

<p>Unlike storyteller&rsquo;s stories, you don&rsquo;t feel like you&rsquo;re riding some kind of high when you&rsquo;re reading these stories. It takes some experience, education and desire to appreciate any kind of craft, either in writing or in furniture. You learn to notice the beautiful seams and delicate details, but most people only see flat lines and somewhere to sit on (or read).</p>

<p>Just as for storytellers, there are the good and bad craftspeople. The good writers focus on creating the best work possible. The bad ones put together a piece of overweening pretentiousness that plays at art, but isn&rsquo;t really art. I&rsquo;ll take the former but leave the latter. In a way, the latter is worse than bad storytellers since they&rsquo;re not even a guilty pleasure.</p>

<h3>Storytellers and Writers Can Play Nice</h3>

<p>You can&rsquo;t compare IKEA with a hand-crafted, one-of-a-kind Shaker furniture. It&rsquo;s not a fair comparison. These companies, just like writers and storytellers, have different goals. Their readers get different things from these books. Storytellers want to enthrall people and their readers want to be entertained. Writers want to create a work of art and their readers want to appreciate art.</p>

<p>Instead of criticizing storytellers for their lack of artiste, one should think about whether these storytellers achieve their goal. look at the plot, the excitement and the enthrall of these stories. Fine prose isn&rsquo;t their goal, nor is it something their readers care about, so should critics care? I&rsquo;m not so sure. I know that, technically speaking, Twilight is a piece of crap, but the series seems to evoke some of teenage girl&rsquo;s most fundamental fantasies and entertain them at the same time. I&rsquo;d have to say despite its glaring flaws, Twilight entertained many of a reader. So, it did &lsquo;succeed&rsquo; at its goal.</p>

<p>For writers, we can apply the more traditional metrics of &ldquo;literary criticism&rdquo; and see if they, in fact, produce a work of art. We shouldn&rsquo;t expect a plot that makes us feel like we&rsquo;re on a high-speed train full of illegal europhic drugs. We should expect a more finely crafted and subtle work.</p>

<p>Of course, there are some people out there who are both storytellers and writers. These are the best of the best. Their stories combine fine art with plot lines that make your heart beat faster. These men and women are the ones that we must truly prize.</p>

<p>For the writers and storytellers, it&rsquo;s only fair to consider them in their own contexts. To compare Twilight with Infinite Jest does both a disservice.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Beyond Genres: Character, Plot and World-Driven Stories]]></title>
    <link href="http://cmmhartmann.com/blog/2013/06/02/beyond-genres-character-plot-world-driven-stories/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-02T19:27:40-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://cmmhartmann.com/blog/2013/06/02/beyond-genres-character-plot-world-driven-stories</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My taste in books spans far and wide. With the single exception of westerns, I&rsquo;ll read any genre. Romance? Yep, been there. (A few writers actually do a wonderful job here.) Sci-fi? Call Mom and tell her I won&rsquo;t be home tonight. Fantasy? Wee.</p>

<p>As I descend into book-alcoholism, I consider myself a bit of a book matchmaker. I try to set up my friends with certain books. As with romantic partner, there&rsquo;s a book out there for everyone.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve noticed that nowadays, genres&rsquo;s predictive power of reader interest is declining. In other words, no longer can a sic-fi buff pick up a new sci-fi book and be certain that he (or she) will appreciate the book.</p>

<p>I suspect it&rsquo;s because genres don&rsquo;t quite capture the appeal of certain books to some readers. I propose a new way of classifying books that capture the book&rsquo;s allure.</p>

<p>I see three different engines that drive different novels:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>World-driven</strong>: the world becomes the book&rsquo;s main attraction. Authors usually spend pages and pages detailing the nooks and crannies of this new, foreign world. The world determines the plot and characters, not the other way around.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Plot-driven</strong>: the plot capiviates and captures the reader. Some strange sequence of events propel the characters towards the climax.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Character-driven</strong>: the character&mdash;his or her development, actions, reactions&mdash;is the novel. The world and plot become secondary to the intimate study of people.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>All novels have a main engine. A world-driven novel can have  an exciting plot, but the world remains the essence of the novel. Likewise for the other categories.</p>

<p>Now, the question arises: why should we care?</p>

<p>As more novels transcend or mix genres, cookie-cutter labels no longer serve as reliable indicator of reader interest. Some &ldquo;science fiction&rdquo; books are primarily character-driven, leading to some disappointment by readers who value world-building over character development.</p>

<p>Some key differences arise among the categories:</p>

<p><strong>World-driven books focus more on the environment, rather than the characters.</strong></p>

<p>By necessity, world-driven books wax endless about the world around the protagonists. This can lead to slow-moving books, and, in the hands of an unskilled writer, stock characters.</p>

<p>Examples include:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><em>Snow Crash</em> (Neal Stephenson): this may be the perfect example of a world-driven novel. Stephenson takes us for a wild ride through a futuristic L.A. County. Currently, I&rsquo;m 45% way through the novel and the plot has barely begun. For readers who prefer quicker-moving books or character development, this book ain&rsquo;t it.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Hard-Boiled Wonderland and the End of the World</em> (Haruki Murakami): a wonderful cyberpunk thriller that combines plot and world-building beautifully. Still, this book leaves character development at the door.</p></li>
<li><p><em>1984</em> (George Orwell): like most dystopian fiction,  <em>1984</em> focuses heavily on the machinations of the thought police and Oceania. Winston Smith serves as a template, showing Big Brother&rsquo;s tyranny.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>All these examples lay with the greats of the greats of literature. World-driven books, in many ways, require more raw creativity than the other two classes. The writer has to devise an original, internally consistent world. That takes real creativity and brainpower.</p>

<p>Certain genres favor this kind of book, such as science fiction, fantasy and dystopias, since these genres are &ldquo;speculative.&rdquo; Don&rsquo;t be fooled. More &ldquo;literary&rdquo; books such as <em>Lord of Flies</em> (William Golding) has a world-driven engine.</p>

<p><strong>Plot-driven novels depend on external events to move along the novel.</strong></p>

<p>Plot consists of events that &ldquo;defines&rdquo; a story. Plot bears very different relationship to the characters and the worlds in different novels. In World-driven novels, the world defines the plot. (Think <em>1984</em> and Winston&rsquo;s efforts to join the Brotherhood). Conversely,  in character-driven novels, characters make the plot possible. (Think: <em>Pride and Prejudice</em> and the rejection scene, followed by Lydia&rsquo;s mishaps.)</p>

<p>Plots work differently in plot-driven works. Plot encapsulates the book itself. It may be more useful to look at examples:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><em>The Count of Monte Cristo</em> (Alexandre Dumas):  the engine of this book is Edmond Dantes&#8217; false imprisonment. Without the treachery of Danglars, Fernand and Villefort, no book would exist. The &ldquo;world&rdquo; is otherwise normal: post-Napoleonic France.  The 19-year-old Edmond Dantes proves too naive and unworldly to drive the novel.</p></li>
<li><p><em>The Girl with the Dragon Tattoo</em> (Stieg Larsson): this premise shocks and enthralls. A woman missing for decades and a sadistic rapist. Even though Mikael Blomvist and Lisbeth Salander are the protagonists, the book isn&rsquo;t truly about them. The book focuses on the strange events of the Vanger family.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Lord of the Rings</em> (J.R. R. Tolkein): I debated whether this series fit the world or the plot-driven category. I think it&rsquo;s more plot-driven since it focuses on Frodo&rsquo;s journey to Mount Doom. The mission to destroy the Ring defines every single character (and the world as well).</p></li>
</ul>


<p>You see, these books lean on the thrilling, exciting side. If one likes plot-driven novels, that generally means one likes snappy, fast-paced books. (Nothing wrong with that!)</p>

<p>Oftentimes, plot-driven novels skimp on character development because the characters serve the plot, not the other way around. A skilled writer, however, can weave character development into the plot.</p>

<p><strong>Character-driven novels focus on the characters: their foibles, follies and triumphs.</strong></p>

<p>Character-driven novels occupy a far corner away from the world and plot-driven novels.  These novels become intimate psychological portrait of a single person (or a few people).</p>

<p>Oftentimes, these books lag and dawdle behind their cohorts. The authors must focus a good chunk of their novel to characterization, development and closure. Sometimes, these novels meander since the characters&mdash;usually quirky and eccentric&mdash;sit in the driver&rsquo;s seat (and they may not drive well). The novel&rsquo;s journey isn&rsquo;t in the events themselves, but in the character development.</p>

<p>Notable examples include:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><em>Pride and Prejudice</em> (Jane Austen): Elizabeth&rsquo;s growth from a prejudiced, sometimes judgmental and willfully blind woman to a more level-headed (but still feisty) woman encompasses the entire novel. Mr. Darcy and her wrong-headed views of each other make the entire rejection scene possible.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Barney&rsquo;s Version</em> (Mordecai Richler): Barney struggles with his worst nemesis: himself. This novel tells a story of an degenerate ingrate grabbing the small happiness that he can, then destroying it. A wonderful, engaging character portrait.</p></li>
<li><p><em>She&rsquo;s Come Undone</em> (Wally Lamb): a heart-wrenching story of a woman struggling with mental illness. This story takes us from Dolores Price&rsquo;s humble beginnings through her struggles with herself and her tenable peace.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Character-driven novels, of course, need characters envelopment. Otherwise, the novel has failed at its entire premise. Books focusing on character development may not excite or enthrall the senses and imagination as much, but they are indeed a worthy read. In the hands of a great author, humanity reveals itself.</p>

<p><strong>So…</strong></p>

<p>You can find all three types in every genre. Of course, some genres favor one type over others. Literature and books today bend and stretch conventional tropes, making genres a less useful predictor for taste.</p>

<p>For example, <em>Graceling</em> shifts the typical world-driven focus of fantasy novels, preferring the character-driven engine. I found it an engaging read, but not all readers did. They have a point. Graceling skimps on world-building, something some readers value above all else. The Game of Thrones (A Song of Ice and Fire&rsquo;s first book) also provides an interesting example of a genre-busting book. There&rsquo;s definitely plot in Games of Thrones, but I think it&rsquo;s far more character-driven than a typical fantasy, with a wide web of character motivations driving the plot forward.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s important to understand the type of novel you prefer. That way, you waste less time with novels that simply don&rsquo;t meet your taste. You can find literature and pure art in all three categories.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t want to abolish genres completely. They serve useful purposes. I want, however, people to truly think about what attracts them to a certain type of book. Is it the world? The plot? Or perhaps, the characters? As noted in the comments with <a href="http://www.quora.com/Monika-Kothari">Monika Kothari</a>, the most ideal use of this categorization would be as a sub-genre. For example, the main genre would be &ldquo;Fantasy&rdquo; sub-divided into world, plot and character-driven categories.</p>

<p>Alas, there will be books that fall somewhere in-between the categories.</p>

<p>Me? I like them all.</p>

<hr />

<p>References:
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Plot_(narrative)">Plot</a> (Wikipedia article)<br/>
<a href="http://www.quora.com/Is-character-development-necessary-for-a-piece-of-literature-to-be-great">Is character development necessary for a piece of literature to be great?</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Authenticity in Fiction: It's Not About Accuracy]]></title>
    <link href="http://cmmhartmann.com/blog/2013/05/15/authenticity-in-fiction-its-not-about-accuracy/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-15T19:52:11-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://cmmhartmann.com/blog/2013/05/15/authenticity-in-fiction-its-not-about-accuracy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As of late, a lot of people have been asking questions about authenticity on Quora.[1][2][3] (Full disclosure: I&rsquo;m one of the askers.)</p>

<p>There is a vague sense that &ldquo;authenticity&rdquo; is important. But we don&rsquo;t quite know what it is. Some will say that it&rsquo;s factual accuracy. Others will say that it&rsquo;s the &ldquo;rightness&rdquo; of the point of view (if that can even be quantified). An even smaller minority will say that it has to <em>feel</em> right.</p>

<p>We just know it&rsquo;s <em>important</em>. So important that many writers spend their lives searching for authenticity/accuracy under history books, rocks, tables and beds. J.R.R. Tolkien created his own language, for god&rsquo;s sake.  Some of them never find it. Some writers just ooze authenticity without opening a single damn book.</p>

<p>If you ask me, I think authenticity is important, but I also think that it isn&rsquo;t what we think it is.</p>

<p><strong>Fiction writers write fiction, not nonfiction.</strong></p>

<p>This statement may seem self-evident, but it&rsquo;s not.</p>

<p>Too many writers chase accuracy as the holy grail. They believe that once they find accuracy, they will have a great story. They look for it everywhere: in the closest, under the bed, on a ship that sails around the world. Unfortunately, many of them conflate <em>accuracy</em> with <em>authenticity</em>.</p>

<p>An accurate story does not a good story make. An accurate story in its purest sense is nonfiction. Maybe the characters are fictional, bu everything else is nonfiction. These writers are writing in the wrong genre.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t get me wrong, I love a good nonfiction, but the genre dosen&rsquo;t serve the same purpose as fiction.Nonfiction tells a story that has happened. Fiction tells a story that has not happened and will most likely never happen.</p>

<p>Because an author gets a few facts wrong&mdash;or even creates a few plot holes&mdash;does not mean that his or her story is a bad story. It just means that it&rsquo;s not nonfiction. If you&rsquo;re reading a story for the factual accuracy, you&rsquo;re in the wrong aisle of the bookstore.</p>

<p>Despite the fact that fiction occupies in a different plane than nonfiction, authenticity and accuracy serve an important purpose. They, however, serve <em>different</em> purposes.</p>

<p><strong>A story must be accurate enough for the reader to suspend their disbelief.</strong></p>

<p>Every fictional story asks the recipient to &ldquo;suspend disbelief.&rdquo; This kind request only goes so far.</p>

<p>If a novel purports to be a historical novel of Regency England, you&rsquo;d raise an eyebrow (and more) if a gentleman said, &ldquo;Whassup Miss Bennet? It&rsquo;s good to see ya!&rdquo; It&rsquo;d take you completely out of your &ldquo;suspend your disbelief&rdquo; state. My example was a bit obvious, but let me give you a more nuanced example. In a book I read recently, the author had 20-year-olds reference <em>Lolita</em> and use &ldquo;whom&rdquo; correctly in colloquial dialogue. <em>That</em> punctured my &ldquo;suspend my disbelief&rdquo; state.</p>

<p>Of course, different readers have different degrees of suspension of his disbelief. That&rsquo;ll happen and frankly, it isn&rsquo;t the author&rsquo;s problem. It&rsquo;s the reader&rsquo;s problem.</p>

<p>A work must be <em>accurate</em> enough to create a believable world that allows readers to suspend their disbelief. Now, this means that the author must do his or her due diligence in researching, but it doesn&rsquo;t mean that the author must <em>live</em> the world to tell a good story. If an author gets the material of 1600s underwear wrong, it&rsquo;s okay as long as readers believe the story.</p>

<p>Of course, one important caveat applies here: <em>context</em>. If the author intends for the work to be a fantastical piece of work that defies credibility, we can hardly demand accuracy (authenticity here is a different issue). If the author wants to write a story where people wear petticoats and text &ldquo;LOL&rdquo; to each other, that&rsquo;s his prerogative. We should only look for accuracy  in works that purport to tell from a non-fantastical point of view.</p>

<p>So, what&rsquo;s authenticity then?</p>

<p><strong>Authenticity&mdash;<em>not</em> accuracy&mdash;is about being true to our dreams and desires. (In other words, true to humanity.)</strong></p>

<p>As most will know from one of my answers, I think emotional authenticity is the most important authenticity of them all.[4]</p>

<p>I may have obfuscated the issue with my terminology. By emotional authenticity, I don&rsquo;t mean writers must only write about <em>accurate</em> emotions. That&rsquo;d be quite limiting. Due to societal constraints, most of us never act on our emotional responses. We have dreams and desires that we never act upon, which seems to be a part of the human condition.</p>

<p>Fictional characters can be allegories for our repressed hopes and dreams. Sometimes, they are the people we wish, with all of our hearts, that we could be. Other fictional characters are the people among us. These characters are so real that we can imagine them sitting next to us on the bus, walking down the grocery store aisles. Both have the ability, in the right hands, to make us love (or hate) them.</p>

<p>Some painters paint a near-exact likeness; other painters paint images where you don&rsquo;t know what&rsquo;s up and what&rsquo;s down. What matters is whether the painting evokes an <em>emotional</em> response from the reader.The two paintings are beautiful in different ways, but are beautiful nevertheless.</p>

<p><strong>Case in point: Quentin Tarantino and &ldquo;wanting to be black.&rdquo;</strong></p>

<p>The discussion about authenticity reminds me the controversy about Quentin Tarantino (director)&rsquo;s focus on black culture and issues in his films. Spike Lee says in a <em>Variety</em> interview,</p>

<blockquote><p>Quentin is infatuated with [the word &ldquo;nigger&rdquo;]. What does he want? To be made into a honorary black man?[5]</p></blockquote>

<p>What Spike Lee is implying here is that Tarantino, since his skin is quite a few shades paler than a black man&rsquo;s, shouldn&rsquo;t get too &ldquo;into&rdquo; black culture since it wouldn&rsquo;t be <em>authentic</em>. (What Lee means here is that Tarantino won&rsquo;t be <em>accurate</em> in showing the black experience.)</p>

<p>Tarantino responds with:</p>

<blockquote><p>As a writer, I demand the right to write any character in the world that I want to write. I demand the right to be them, I demand the right to think them and I demand the right to tell the truth as I see they are, all right? And to say that I can&rsquo;t do that because I&rsquo;m white, but the Hughes brothers can do that because they&rsquo;re black, that is racist.[5]</p></blockquote>

<p>Tarantino may seem a poor example of authenticity, since he directs and write revenge thrillers. In <em>Inglorious Basterds</em>, he revised history to have a Jewish scalping squad and to off Hitler. In <em>Django Unchained</em>, Tarantino, once again revises history to have the slaves rise up against their masters.</p>

<p>Tarantino isn&rsquo;t trying to be accurate since every history book contradicts him. He&rsquo;s not even trying to be true to &ldquo;realistic&rdquo; human actions. (Last time I checked, most people didn&rsquo;t gather samurai swords and hunt down their enemies.) But where Tarantino&rsquo;s storytelling genius lies&mdash;and this is as authentic as it gets&mdash;is his understanding of our <strong>desire for revenge</strong>.</p>

<p>Most of us will never tell the boss whom we hate (the ass keeps us late at work when he goes to meet his mistress). But as we sit in our gray cubicle, we dream about getting that damn sword and offing that megalomanic jerk. We want to be these people on the screen, putting it to the bad guys. We will probably never be that person, but Quentin understands that. Quentin has tapped into a truly <em>authentic</em> part of humanity: or repressed dreams of vengeance.</p>

<p><strong>Authenticity isn&rsquo;t about <em>accuracy</em>, it&rsquo;s about being true to the human condition. It&rsquo;s fiction, not nonfiction.</strong></p>

<hr />

<p>[1]: <a href="http://www.quora.com/Writing/What-is-authenticity-in-writing">Writing: What is authenticity in writing?</a><br/>
[2]: <a href="http://www.quora.com/Writing/Is-it-possible-for-writers-to-write-about-an-emotion-authentically-without-ever-experiencing-it-directly">Writing: Is it possible for writers to write about an emotion authentically without ever experiencing it directly?</a><br/>
[3]: <a href="http://www.quora.com/Writing/What-are-good-ways-to-research-and-write-authentic-period-dialogue">Writing: What are good ways to research and write authentic period dialogue?</a><br/>
[4]: <a href="http://www.quora.com/Writing/Is-it-possible-for-writers-to-write-about-an-emotion-authentically-without-ever-experiencing-it-directly/answer/Cristina-Hartmann">Cristina Hartmann&rsquo;s answer to Writing: Is it possible for writers to write about an emotion authentically without ever experiencing it directly?</a><br/>
[5]: <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quentin_Tarantino#Racial_epithets_in_Tarantino.27s_work">Racial Epithets in Tarantino&rsquo;s Work</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Give Good Feedback on Creative Stuff]]></title>
    <link href="http://cmmhartmann.com/blog/2013/05/07/how-to-give-good-feedback-on-creative-stuff/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-07T20:14:50-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://cmmhartmann.com/blog/2013/05/07/how-to-give-good-feedback-on-creative-stuff</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks ago, I talked about <a href="http://cmmhartmann.com/blog/2013/04/09/how-to-get-feedback-on-your-writing-or-other-stuff">How to Get Feedback on Your Writing</a>. One of the cardinal suggestions was to provide good feedback, but I neglected to explain how.</p>

<p>Let me rectify that oversight.</p>

<p>Giving feedback is a skill worth developing, particularly in creative endeavors where good feedback can take something from mediocre to awesome. Good feedback doesn&rsquo;t just benefit the recipient; it benefits the provider as well. Giving good, cogent feedback on others&#8217; work will sharpen your assessment of your own work. Plus, giving terrible feedback just may earn you an enemy, rather than a friend.</p>

<p>So, it&rsquo;s win-win.</p>

<p>My advice will focus mostly on writers and writing, but I hope it can be generalized to other creative areas.</p>

<p><strong>Tailor your feedback to the stage of the project.</strong></p>

<p>There are two basic types of feedback in writing: meta-level and micro-level types. Meta-level feedback pertain to &ldquo;big idea&rdquo; issues like plot, structure and character development. Micro-level feedback has more to do with prose: sentence structure, word flow, and voice.</p>

<p>Both types of feedback are crucial to writers, but their helpfulness depend on the timing. Picking out typos or grammar mishaps is probably a waste of time in a first draft since these sentences may not survive the subsequent redrafting. Meta-level feedback can be harmful at the latest stages of a work, since it may instill doubt and needless redrafting by the writer. Timing matters.</p>

<p>Projects that are in the early stages of development benefit the most from meta-level feedback; late-stage projects get the polish it needs from micro-level feedback.</p>

<p><strong>Understand the project&rsquo;s context and objectives.</strong></p>

<p>There&rsquo;s nothing more frustrating than getting feedback that missed or misunderstood the context or objective of my writing. The feedback ends up being worse than useless. It wastes time on two sides: the giver&rsquo;s and the receiver&rsquo;s.</p>

<p>Fictional works geared towards young adults require a different set of criteria and concerns than works aimed at adults. To give good feedback, you need to understand what the writer&rsquo;s goal and audience are. Otherwise, you may lead them astray by accident.</p>

<p>Oftentimes, that means you&rsquo;ll need to ask questions before you start commenting.</p>

<p><strong>Be clear and precise in your feedback.</strong></p>

<p>This goes for both positive and negative feedback.</p>

<p>&ldquo;I liked it! It was nice!&rdquo; is always nice to hear, but isn&rsquo;t terribly helpful. I&rsquo;m unclear what you liked about my story. It could be anything: the prose, the plot, the cute guy on page 88. &ldquo;I liked how the story looped back to the beginning. It gave me a lot of closure,&rdquo; is a lot more helpful (and gratifying).</p>

<p>Likewise, &ldquo;The father&rsquo;s outburst is weird. I don&rsquo;t like it,&rdquo; is less than helpful. &ldquo;The father&rsquo;s outburst seems like it came out of nowhere and isn&rsquo;t well-developed,&rdquo; works much better. The latter gives me something I can work with, a goal. The former doesn&rsquo;t.</p>

<p>Clarity and precision in your feedback allows the recipient to figure out what your feedback means. General feedback usually end up sounding like personal, subjective opinions which can be easily discarded.</p>

<p>Of course, clarity and precision will take hard work and some thinking.</p>

<p><strong>Treat feedback as a conversation rather than a lecture.</strong></p>

<p>Sometimes when I get feedback, I&rsquo;ll think to myself, &ldquo;I&rsquo;m not so sure about that.&rdquo; So I counter with my own opinion of the particular segment.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t do this to be an egoistical jerk (I pinky swear). I argue a bit with a reader to see if the feedback is reliable and consistent. Sometimes, readers will miss a key detail that I included that changes their opinion or interpretation. If so, I will either disregard the feedback or think about making the detail more prominent. If, however, the reader simply slinks off and sulks, I usually don&rsquo;t take their feedback seriously. It ended up feeling like someone was lecturing me, but that someone was completely unlearned in that subject.</p>

<p>As a writer, I&rsquo;ve found the best feedback to come <em>after</em> a conversation with a reader. Sometimes the conversation gleans deeper insight than the original piece of feedback. It also led to a nice friendship.</p>

<p>At the end, it takes two to create a great critique experience: the provider and the recipient.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to Get Feedback on Your Writing (or Other Stuff)]]></title>
    <link href="http://cmmhartmann.com/blog/2013/04/09/how-to-get-feedback-on-your-writing-or-other-stuff/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-09T20:10:09-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://cmmhartmann.com/blog/2013/04/09/how-to-get-feedback-on-your-writing-or-other-stuff</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>No matter what our pretensions are, no writer can spin out a perfect story  by themselves. Feedback has the potential to push your work to the next level.</p>

<p>Great! But&hellip;<em>how</em> do you get feedback?</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve been at this long enough to know it isn&rsquo;t easy, but it&rsquo;s not impossible.  Here are a few things that I&rsquo;ve learned (and I still have some more to learn):</p>

<p><strong>Like cold-calling, cold-requesting rarely works.</strong></p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a reason why cold-calling investors has a miserable success rate. It&rsquo;s somewhat creepy and nobody wants to be interrupted during dinnertime. People don&rsquo;t trust strangers and door-to-door salesmen.</p>

<p>You may get lucky, but the odds are against you.</p>

<p><strong>Form friendships with like-minded people.</strong></p>

<p>It was only when I started to befriend other writers when I started to get quality feedback. Their feedback is worth its weight in gold since they have a deep understanding of what it takes to write. Plus, I try to befriend cool people, so the feedback is just a fringe benefit.</p>

<p>A <em>big</em> caveat here: you need to be real friends with them.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s human nature. People are far more willing to part with 100 dollars for a dear friend thant they are willing to part with five cents for a street beggar. We seem to have an instinctual willingness to help the ones close to us.</p>

<p><strong>Be generous with your thoughts and time.</strong></p>

<p>This is closely related to the previous point. It&rsquo;s hard to make friends if you&rsquo;re a selfish miser; just look at Ebenzener Scrooge in The <em>Christmas Carol</em>. I&rsquo;m pretty sure he couldn&rsquo;t find anyone to critique his storefront design.</p>

<p>Give people good, thoughtful feedback. Most people will return the favor. You don&rsquo;t even necessarily need to be generous with your feedback, but you do need to be generous with your time and kindness.</p>

<p>Most people&mdash;selfish misers excepted&mdash;have the natural tendency to want to return favors. Kindness has a way of coming back to you, one way or another.</p>

<p><strong>Realize that you will get about 20% yield on feedback.</strong></p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t expect everyone, even your bestest friend in the whole wide world, to deliver on their feedback. It takes time and energy, something that people don&rsquo;t always have.</p>

<p>So, even in the bast-case scenario, you will have to prepare to do certain things by yourself. Hopefully you have enough good, smart friends to make up the difference.</p>

<p><strong>Regardless of the feedback&rsquo;s content, always be gracious.</strong></p>

<p>You&rsquo;ll get lucky and someone gives you feedback&hellip;except that it&rsquo;s bad. Some of the &ldquo;bad&rdquo; feedback will point out flaws in your work. Other will just be bad.</p>

<p>No matter what they say, you always, <em>always</em>, say, &ldquo;Thank you. I will look into it.&rdquo; You can even ask questions and try to clarify their thinking, but do not attack them outright.They gave their time to you, and that is worth some politeness (even if the person isn&rsquo;t).</p>

<p>You just look way classier this way. Others will notice.</p>

<p><strong>Ask specific questions to get better feedback.</strong></p>

<p>Okay, so you&rsquo;ve finally gotten some people to give you feedback. You ask them, &ldquo;So, what did you think?&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;Uh&hellip;I don&rsquo;t like the main character&rsquo;s name. It was fine otherwise&rdquo;</p>

<p>Giving feedback is a rare talent. Most people need to be guided. This will require some serious work on  your part and substantial self-awareness. You&rsquo;ll have to assess your project&rsquo;s potential weak spots. It&rsquo;s hard, but you can do it.</p>

<p>Try this instead:</p>

<p>&ldquo;What did you think about the conflicts between the protagonist and her father?&rdquo;</p>

<p>&ldquo;I thought it was exciting, but too rushed. I felt like the fight was done with too quickly.&rdquo;</p>

<p><em>That</em> feedback you can really use.</p>

<p>Getting feedback is hard. Knowing what to do with it is harder.</p>

<p><em>Comments and suggestions welcome, particularly in regards to the ordering of this list. I&rsquo;m glad to discuss anything that I missed as well.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
